Guide to the Norman Douglas Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Norman Douglas Collection
1864-2000
1920-1980
GEN MSS 88
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
27.51
(63 boxes) + 1 art
Douglas, Norman, 1868-1952
Lyons, Islay, 1922-1993
Macpherson, Kenneth
Magnus, Maurice, 1876-1920
Immediate Source of Acquisition
I. 1968-1993 Acquisitions: This group is made up of a number of separate acquisitions received by the library from 1968 to 1993. The largest of these are the 1968 purchase of David G. Jeffreys's collection, purchased on the Beinecke Fund (Kitty Miller), and the 1972 and 1975 gifts of Kenneth Macpherson. A detailed list of sources for material in this collection is located in Box 1.
II. 1993-2003 Acquisitions: Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
III. January 2008 Acquisition: Purchased from Elysium Press on The Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 2008.
IV. August 2008 Acquisition: Purchased from Elysium Press on The Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Norman Douglas (1868-1952)
Norman Douglas, an expatriate British author, was born in Thüringen, Austria. Educated in Scotland and Europe, he entered the British diplomatic service in 1893 and left three years later. Douglas married Elsa FitzGibbon in 1898. The couple had two sons before divorcing in 1904. Douglas was assistant editor for The English Review from 1912-1916, during which he authored the travel books Siren Land (1911), Fountains in the Sand (1912), and Old Calabria (1915). In 1916 he left London for Capri, where he wrote the novel South Wind (1917). During the 1920s and 1930s Douglas continued to publish fiction, essays, travel books, and autobiographical works, many in limited editions published by his companion Pino Orioli. After the outbreak of World War II, Douglas fled to London from Lisbon, and returned to Capri in 1946. His later works were Late Harvest (1946), and the posthumously-published Venus in the Kitchen (1952), which he edited under the pseudonym Pilaff Bey.
Scope and Contents
The Norman Douglas Collection chiefly documents Douglas's writing career, personal life, and relationships with other writers and artists. Although the collection spans the years 1864-2000, the bulk of the papers fall in the period 1920-1980. The collection contains material created and accumulated by Norman Douglas, Kenneth Macpherson, Islay de Courcy Lyons, and Maurice Magnus. Material includes correspondence, writings, diaries, photographs, photograph albums, financial and business papers, personal effects, printed material, artwork, and a bronze sculpture.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: I. 1968-1993 Acquisitions. II. 1993-2003 Acquisitions. III. January 2008 Acquisition. IV. August 2008 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized in groups reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time.
Researchers should note that material within each group overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other groups. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each group described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each group, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
British literature -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Busts (figures); H. D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1886-1961; Ouida, 1839-1908; Benton, Kay Hutchinson; Bryher, 1894-1983; Cullen, Charles; Cunard, Nancy, 1896-1965; Douglas, Archibald, 1899-; Douglas, Norman, 1868-1952; Douglas, Robin, 1902-; Garnett, Edward, 1868-1937; Hutchinson, F. W.; Jeffreys, D. G. (David G.); King, William; Levy, Oscar, 1867-1946; Lyons, Islay, 1922-1993; Macpherson, Kenneth; Magnus, Maurice, 1876-1920; Mavrogordato, John, 1882-; Orioli, Giuseppe, 1884-1942; Phillpotts, Eden, 1862-1960; Strachey, Lytton, 1880-1932; Tomlinson, H. M. (Henry Major), 1873-1958; Woolf, Cecil
- 1968-1993 Acquisitions, 1864-1967; Series I; 16.31; (42 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into five series: I. Writings. II. Correspondence. III. Subject Files. IV. Personal Papers. V. Material Related to Norman Douglas.
  Scope and Contents
  The 1968-1993 Acquisitions chiefly document Norman Douglas's writing career. Although the collection spans the years 1864-1967, the bulk of the papers date between 1920 and 1950.
  Series I. Writings, documents the creation and publication of many of Douglas's works. Series II. Correspondence, includes letters to and from Douglas and a substantial quantity of third party correspondence. Literary manuscripts and other papers Douglas acquired can be found in Series III. Subject Files. Series IV. Personal Papers, contains records related to Douglas's private life and family papers. Material Related to Norman Douglas, Series V., is comprised of a variety of material, from published articles to radio broadcast scripts, about Douglas and his work.
  - Writings, 1880-1956; Series I
    Organized into three subseries: Books and Pamphlets, Contributions to Books and Pamphlets, and Contributions to Periodicals. This arrangement is informed by Cecil Woolf's A Bibliography of Norman Douglas (London: Rupert Hart-Davis, 1954). Within each edition, the material is placed in order of creation, from the author's notes to printed versions. Miscellaneous works are at the end of each section. Documents that cannot be assigned to a specific edition are placed under "Unidentified editions." The arrangement of background material, drafts, and reviews follows the order of production.
    Series I. chiefly consists of: research material and notes, manuscript drafts, typescripts, galleys, printer's proofs, printed versions, clippings, and correspondence.
    Research material comprises documents Douglas collected as background sources, while notes are papers he produced. Douglas made extensive use of newspaper clippings when writing Old Calabria and Siren Land, while London Street Games was based on scores of children's letters. Douglas's own notes can be found for Birds and Beasts and Some Limericks. An interesting document is Douglas's memo on the arrangement of Late Harvest, which was not printed during Douglas's lifetime.
    The series includes manuscript drafts for most of Douglas's later works. The majority of typescripts, galleys, and printer's proofs are extensively corrected, although the presence of multiple copies with similar markings makes it difficult to discern the order of the drafts. In such contingencies the term "variant copies" has been used to alert the user. Typescripts, galleys, and printer's proofs were often inscribed by Douglas and given to friends, especially Kenneth Macpherson and David Jeffreys.
    Almost every book represented in the series has a clippings file containing reviews and advertisements. The documentation for several works includes business correspondence and fan mail. Fan mail predominates, as in the case of Old Calabria and London Street Games, where readers sent Douglas further information on his topic.
    Other material in this series concerns dramatizations of Douglas's prose. There are notices of stage and radio performances, and a playscript for They Went.
    - Books and Pamphlets
      - On the Herpetology of Baden (1894)
        - Manuscript draft, [1888] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Report on Pumice Stone Industry (1895)
        - Printed version, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - On the Darwinian Hypothesis (1895)
        - Manuscript draft, "Author's Notes", [1951] (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Siren Land (1911)
        - 1911 edition: correspondence, 1911, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - 1923 edition: clipping, [circa 1923] (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - 1948 edition
          - Galleys, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
          - Illustration, [ca. 1948] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Fountains in the Sand
        - 1912 edition: manuscript draft in 2 volumes, circa 1912 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      - Disiecta Membra
        - 1915 edition: manuscript draft in 2 volumes, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
      - Old Calabria (1915)
        - 1915 British edition
          - Research material, 1880s-1914 (Box 2, Folder 12)
          - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - 1920 edition: clipping, 1927 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - 1927 edition: clippings, 1928 May (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - [1930] edition: corrections (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - 1938 edition
          - Manuscript drafts: introduction, [1938] (Box 2, Folder 17)
          - Typescript: introduction, [1938] (Box 2, Folder 18)
        - 1955 edition: clippings, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Unidentified editions
          - Clippings, 1925, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 20)
          - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Dramatization, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - London Street Games (1916)
        - 1916 edition
          - Research material, [circa 1915] (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
            Related Archival Materials note
            See also: Oversize, Box 42, folder 646
          - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - 1931 edition
          - Manuscript draft: index, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
          - Typescript: preface, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
          - Typescript: index (variant copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
          - Printer's proofs (variant copies), 1931 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
          - Clippings, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 33)
          - Correspondence, 1931, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 34)
        - Unidentified editions: miscellaneous, 1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - South Wind (1917)
        - 1917 edition
          - Research material, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
          - Clippings, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 37)
        - 1918 edition: dust-jacket (Box 3, Folder 38)
        - 1925 edition: typescript, introduction, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 39)
        - 1928 edition: clipping (Box 3, Folder 40)
        - 1929 illustrated edition: clipping (Box 3, Folder 41)
        - 1932 edition: clipping, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 42)
        - 1939 edition: clipping (Box 3, Folder 43)
        - Unidentified editions
          - Correspondence, 1917-1951 (Box 3, Folder 44)
          - Miscellaneous, 1922-1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
        - Dramatizations, 1949-1955 (Box 3, Folder 46-48)
      - They Went (1920)
        - 1920 edition
          - Typescript, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 49)
            Laid in volume: letter to unidentified recipient from G. Orioli dated 1929 April 13.
          - Printer's proofs, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 50)
        - Unidentified editions
          - Correspondence, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 51)
          - Miscellaneous, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 52)
        - Dramatization, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Alone (1921)
        - Unidentified edition: illustration, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Together (1923)
        - Miscellaneous, 1946, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Lawrence & Magnus (1925)
        - Typescript, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 56)
        - Printer's proofs (variant copies), [1924] (Box 4, Folder 57-59)
        - Correspondence, H. G. Wells, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Experiments (1925)
        - 1925 British edition: typescript- printed draft (Box 4, Folder 61)
        - 1925 British edition: "Blind Guides" print version from The English Review and offprint (?) from Experiments, p. 59-76 (Box 4, Folder 62)
        - 1925 British edition: Book reviews, manuscript drafts and offprint (?) from Experiments, p. 127-32 (Box 4, Folder 63)
        - 1925 British edition: Book reviews, manuscript drafts and offprint (?) from Experiments, p. 207-13 (Box 4, Folder 64)
        - 1926 American edition: clipping (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Birds and Beasts of the Greek Anthology (1927)
        - 1927 edition
          - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
          - Manuscript draft: introduction, undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
          - Manuscript draft: index, undated (Box 5, Folder 68)
          - Typescript: introduction, undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
          - Typescript: index, undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
          - Galleys: index, [1927] (Box 5, Folder 71)
          - Printer's proofs, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 72)
          - Clippings, 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 73)
        - 1928 edition
          - Printer's proofs, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 74)
          - Clippings, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 75)
        - 1929 edition: clipping, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 76)
        - Unidentified editions: miscellaneous, 1928, undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - In the Beginning (1927)
        - 1927 edition
          - Manuscript draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 78-79)
          - Typescripts (variant copies), undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
          - Printed version (variant copies), 1927 (Box 7, Folder 81)
        - 1953 edition: clipping (Box 7, Folder 82)
      - Some Limericks (1928)
        - 1928 edition
          - Notes, 1928, undated (Box 7, Folder 83-77)
          - Manuscript draft: introduction, undated (Box 7, Folder 88)
          - Typescript: introduction, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
          - Typescript, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 90)
          - Printer's proofs (variant copies), 1928 (Box 7, Folder 91-92)
        - Unidentified editions
          - Correspondence, 1928, 1934, undated (Box 7, Folder 93)
          - Miscellaneous, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 94)
      - Nerinda (1929)
        - 1929 edition
          - Drafts: "Author's Note", [circa 1929] (Box 7, Folder 95)
          - Typescript: [Author's Note], [circa 1929] (Box 7, Folder 96)
          - Typescript, [circa 1929] (Box 7, Folder 97)
          - Galleys, [1929] (Box 8, Folder 98)
          - Printer's proof, [1929] (Box 8, Folder 99)
        - 1929 American edition: clipping (Box 8, Folder 100)
      - One Day (1929)
        - Manuscript draft, undated (Box 8, Folder 101)
      - How About Europe (1929)
        - 1929 edition
          - Research material, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 102)
          - Galleys, [1929] (Box 8, Folder 103)
          - Printer's Proof, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 104-05)
        - 1930 American edition: clippings (Box 8, Folder 106)
        - 1930 British edition: clippings (Box 8, Folder 107)
        - Unidentified editions: clippings, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 108)
      - Capri (1930)
        - Research material, undated (Box 9, Folder 111)
        - Manuscript draft: index, [circa 1930] (Box 9, Folder 112)
        - Printer's proofs (variant copies), [1930] (Box 9, Folder 113-24)
        - Printer's proofs (variant copies), [1930] (Box 10, Folder 125)
        - Illustration, undated (Box 10, Folder 126)
        - Clipping, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 127)
        - Three of Them (1930)
          - Printer's proofs, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 109)
          - Clippings, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 110)
      - Paneros (1930)
        - 1930 edition
          - Research material, undated (Box 10, Folder 128-30)
          - Typescript, [1930] (Box 10, Folder 131)
          - Galleys (variant copies), [1930] (Box 10, Folder 132-34)
          - Printer's proofs (variant copies), 1930 (Box 11, Folder 135-38)
          - Clippings, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 139)
          - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 140)
        - 1931 edition: clippings (Box 11, Folder 141)
        - 1932 edition: clipping (Box 11, Folder 142)
        - Unidentified editions: miscellaneous, undated (Box 11, Folder 143)
      - Summer Islands (1931)
        - Clippings, 1931-1932 (Box 11, Folder 144)
      - Looking Back (1933)
        - 1933 edition
          - Research material, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 145-47)
          - Manuscript draft, [circa 1933] (Box 12, Folder 148)
          - Typescript (variant copies), [1933] (Box 12, Folder 149)
          - Typescript (variant copies), [1933] (Box 13, Folder 150-51)
          - Clippings, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 152)
          - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 153)
          - Miscellaneous, [1933] (Box 13, Folder 154)
        - 1933 American edition: clippings (Box 13, Folder 155)
        - 1934 edition: clippings (Box 13, Folder 156)
        - Unidentified editions: correspondence, 1933-1936 (Box 13, Folder 157)
      - Almanac (1941)
        - Clippings, 1945-1946 (Box 13, Folder 158)
      - Late Harvest (1946)
        - Notes, [circa 1946] (Box 13, Folder 159-60)
        - Manuscript draft, [circa 1946] (Box 14, Folder 161)
        - Typescript (variant copies), [1946] (Box 14, Folder 162-75)
        - Typescript (variant copies), [1946] (Box 15, Folder 176-77)
        - Typescript: index, [1946] (Box 15, Folder 178-81)
        - Galleys, [1946] (Box 15, Folder 182)
        - Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box 15, Folder 183)
        - Typescript: "Author's Note", [1948] (Box 15, Folder 184)
        - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 15, Folder 185)
      - Footnote on Capri (1952)
        - Manuscript draft, undated (Box 15, Folder 186-87)
        - Typescripts, undated (Box 15, Folder 188-93)
        - Clippings, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 194)
      - Miscellaneous
        - ["Capri"]: Manuscript draft, undated (Box 15, Folder 195)
        - "A Little Discovery:" typescripts (variant copies), undated (Box 15, Folder 196)
        - "Love Among The Ruins": manuscript draft, [1928] (Box 15, Folder 197)
        - [Preface to an edition of selected works], undated (Box 15, Folder 198)
    - Contributions to Books and Pamphlets
      - That Capri Air: "Cestosina"
        - Manuscript draft, [circa 1926] (Box 15, Folder 199)
        - Clipping, 1926 (Box 15, Folder 200)
      - The Last of the Medici: "Introduction"
        - Manuscript draft, [circa 1930] (Box 15, Folder 201)
        - Typescript, [1930] (Box 16, Folder 202)
      - Negro: "A Letter From Arusha"
        - Manuscript draft, [circa 1934] (Box 16, Folder 203)
      - Venus in the Kitchen
        - Preface: manuscript draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 204)
        - Typescript (of entire work), [1936, 1951] (Box 16, Folder 205)
        - Frontspiece: photograph and glass negative, undated (Box 16, Folder 206)
        - Clippings, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 207)
    - Contributions to Periodicals
      - "Another Source of Paradise Lost"
        - "Milton in Calabria:" printed version, 1936 (Box 16, Folder 208)
        - "On Paradise Lost"
          - Manuscript draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 209)
          - Typescript, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 210-11)
          - Galleys, [1948] (Box 16, Folder 212-13)
          - Printer's proofs, [1948] (Box 16, Folder 214-15)
          - Printed version, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 216)
          - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 217)
      - [Review of] Ouida: A Memoir
        - Printed versions, 1914 (Box 16, Folder 218)
      - [Review of] Justice of the Peace
        - Manuscript draft and typescripts, [1915] (Box 16, Folder 219)
      - [Review of] Arabia Deserta
        - Printer's proofs, [1921] (Box 16, Folder 220)
      - "Something From Beyond"
        - "Queer": printed versions, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 221)
      - "Some Comments on My Books"
        - Manuscript draft, [1943] (Box 16, Folder 222)
      - Miscellaneous
        - [Review of] "Bubi"
          - Notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 223)
          - Manuscript draft, [circa 1932] (Box 16, Folder 224)
  - Correspondence, 1874-1960; Series II
    Series II is organized into three subseries: Norman Douglas Incoming Correspondence, Norman Douglas Outgoing Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence. The first two subseries contain letters to and from Norman Douglas, arranged alphabetically by name and then chronologically. Correspondents with fewer than five letters have been placed in "Letter" general files. Third Party Correspondence consists of letters to and from Robin Douglas, F. W. Hutchinson, D. H. Lawrence, Kenneth Macpherson, and Maurice Magnus. Where there is more then one party corresponding with an individual, the letters are listed under individual names.
    Series II includes incoming, outgoing, and third party correspondence that document the professional and private life of Norman Douglas. Most of Douglas's correspondents were members of the literary world, and they discussed contemporary authors and their works. The English Review file concerns Douglas's editorial work, while the Grant Richards Ltd. Publishers file documents Douglas's role as Maurice Magnus's literary executor. Information on the publication of Douglas's own work is abundant. Correspondence with The Bookseller documents the copyright problems relating to South Wind, and the letters of Edward Garnett, Willie (William) King, Oscar Levy, and John Mavrogordato are filled with editorial advice.
    With a few friends, Douglas's letters were more intimate. In his correspondence with Bryher, Martha Gordon-Crotch, David Jeffreys, and Kenneth Macpherson, he writes of the young men in his life. Series II also contains correspondence with these male companions (see Emilio Papa, Rene Mari, and Eric Wolton). Douglas wrote frequently to his son Archibald and the collection contains his letters from 1925 to Douglas's death in 1952. The letters discuss literature as well as Douglas's own writing and document the lives of Douglas and Archibald.
    Third party correspondence consists of letters to and from Robin Douglas, F. W. Hutchinson, D. H. Lawrence, Kenneth Macpherson, and Maurice Magnus. The letters of Robin Douglas and Kenneth Macpherson comment on the press's treatment of Douglas. Hutchinson's correspondence sheds light on Douglas's difficulties during World War II, especially Hutchinson's letters to Nancy Cunard.
    The series also contains a large number of early twentieth century Italian postcards. Douglas sent cards depicting Italian sculpture and architecture to F. W. and Kay Hutchinson, Kenneth Macpherson, and John Mavrogordato.
    - Norman Douglas Incoming Correspondence
      - "A" general, 1913-1926 (Box 17, Folder 225-26)
        Including
        Harold Acton (2)
        Douglas Ainslie
        Michael Arlen (2)
      - "B" general, 1895-1952 (Box 17, Folder 227-28)
        Sylvia Beach
        Lord Beaverbrook
        E. F. Benson
        Robert Bridges
        Robert Byron (2)
      - The Bookseller, 1943 (Box 17, Folder 229)
      - Bowski, Adolf, 1914-1923 (Box 17, Folder 230)
      - "C" general, 1914-1949 (Box 17, Folder 231)
        Aleister Crowley
        Irene Colvin (3)
        Geoffrey Cookson (2)
      - Conrad, Jessie, 1905-1936 (Box 17, Folder 232)
      - Conrad, Joseph, 1905-1912, undated (Box 17, Folder 233)
      - Cullen, Charles, 1929-1931 (Box 17, Folder 234)
      - "D" general, 1912-1938 (Box 17, Folder 235)
        Arundel del Re
        Edward Dent
        Muriel Draper
        John Drinkwater (2)
      - Douglas, Archibald, 1921, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 236)
      - Douglas, Mary, 1903 April 9 (Box 17, Folder 237)
      - Douglas, Robin, 1928-1930 (Box 17, Folder 238-39)
      - Douglas, Uretta, 1929-1930 (Box 17, Folder 240)
      - Douglas family, 1881, 1894 (Box 17, Folder 241)
      - Douglass, Jane, 1874-1988 (Box 17, Folder 242)
      - "E" general, 1913-1936, undated (Box 17, Folder 243)
        Arthur Eckersley (2)
      - The English Review, 1912-1913, undated (Box 17, Folder 244)
        See also: Box 17, folder 256 and Box 19, folder 309
      - "F" general, 1913-1936, undated (Box 17, Folder 245)
      - Forster, E. M., 1917-1927 (Box 17, Folder 246)
      - Freud, Sigmund, 1933 (Box 17, Folder 247)
      - "G" general, 1913-1948 (Box 17, Folder 248)
        André Gide
        Graham Greene
      - Garnett, Edward, 1911-1927, undated (Box 17, Folder 249)
      - Gordon-Crotch, Martha, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 250)
      - Grant Richards, Ltd. Publishers, 1917-1923 (Box 17, Folder 251)
      - Gulbransson, Anyuta, undated (Box 17, Folder 252)